Guide to the McCarthy era newspaper clippings, 1946-1954
Department of Special Collections
McCarthy era newspaper clippings,
1946-1954
Special Collections M0186
Stanford University. Office of the President.
2 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Gift of the Stanford University President's Office.
Scope and Content
Newspaper clippings the subject of which is subversive activities and the resulting investigations in the United States. Topics covered are: the Smith Act, the Tenney Bill, the Levering Act, the University of California special loyalty oath, the McCarran Act, McCarthyism, academic freedom, and the Rosenberg trials, with special sections on the Everitt Hudson (Stanford student) case and press and government censorship. Also some minor topics included.
CONTAINER LIST
- Contains political cartoons, articles from The Palo Alto Times, The San Francisco News, and other Bay area newspapers plus representation from other major tabloids. Articles on Stanford personnel and professors taking political stand. Deals mainly with professors' public stands and resulting actions. Also some letters to the Editors and some articles dealing with the U. C. loyalty oath. Special section on the Hudson case., 1946 - 1950 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Generally the same sort of topics as covered above. More on loyalty oaths, student and academic stances on political developments. Articles on the development of McCarthyism. Some reaction to same., 1951 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Looming threat of newspaper censorship discussed. A few [UNK] covered. Exploitation of sensationalism factor (e.g. 2/8/52 article on Communist sex orgies). Various prestige universities defend teachers' and students' rights to public opinion. Sterling says Stanford not place for committed communist. McCarthy investigation continues. Singer Paul Robeson denied concert hall, then almost deported., 1952 Jan.-Aug. (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Rosenberg trials covered. Evidence and accusations of McCarthy's use of fraud, perjury, and calculated deceit prevalent. Red panic and resulting rumors rampant. Alger Hiss' case much disseminated by comunists, reporters., 1952 Sept.-Dec. (Box 2, Folder 4)
- McCarthy will probe colleges. McCarthy asks for medals. College subversive hunt on. Rosenberg trial and appeal lost. Subsequent Rosenberg reactions. Tarantino affair covered. Velde case covered. Panic over reds running out of hand and fanaticism carried to absurdity., 1953 Jan.-Mar. (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Political cartoons. Emphasis on the colleg es' part in the purge of communists. Nixon as mediator between Eisenhower-McCarthy rivalry. McCarthy's financial affairs (i.e. donations to fight against communism) questioned. Oath is schools, oaths for housing projects, oaths for paying taxes (!). Browbeating witnesses to confess in Smith hearings. Rosenberg's death date set., 1953 Apr.-May (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Book burnings. Criticism against McCarthy growing. Book ban affairs. McCarthy increasingly more unpopular and brunt of criticism., 1953 July-Aug. (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Moderation in McCarthy's fanaticism sought. Truman subpoenaed - not even president's are safe. Articles in the same vein and general subject matter as in preceding scrapbooks., 1953 Sept.-Nov. (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Eisenhower steps in. McCarthy goes overboard (i.e. Harvard, 11/23). McCarthyism going. Rosenberg affair continues., 1953 Nov. 16-Dec. (Box 3, Folder 9)
- McCarthy being fenced in. Articles as above. Rosenberg affiars continue., 1954 Jan.-Feb. (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Rosenbergs trial affairs. Section on press and government censorship., 1953 June -- Censorship'47-'54 (Box 4, Folder 11)